Chi?
阿潘
What brings you here?
你怎么在这儿
The new scribe, Lady Yan.
颜令史
It's been a while.
好久不见
This is a crime scene.
查案重地
How could you allow
怎么可以随意让
unrelated individuals to enter?
不相关的人进来
You've misunderstood, Lord Shen.
大阁领误会了
This gentleman
此位
is the top detective in the realm.
乃是民间第一神探
Mr. Pan Chi.
潘驰潘郎君
He's here to assist me
此行也是协助下官
with the investigation,
前来查案的
not an unrelated individual.
并非是不相关之人
Greetings, Lord Shen.
沈大阁领
So,
果然
it seems the rumors are true.
传闻都是真的
Chi is indeed Pan Chi.
阿潘就是潘驰
You can always
你也可以
think of me
永远把那个阿潘
as just Chi.
就当成是那个阿潘
I happened to come across this case.
我也是碰巧遇到此事
At the request of the suspect's
受嫌犯妹夫所托
brother-in-law, I came to investigate.
前来调查
When the suspect was apprehended,
这嫌犯刚被抓的时候
he was found unarmed
身上可是一干二净
without any trace of weapons.
且没有任何凶器
I suspect
我怀疑
he might have been wronged.
他极有可能是被冤枉的
The case file indicates
卷宗里面写过
the victim's brother
死者的弟弟
doesn't practice martial arts at all,
并非习武之人
making him an unlikely suspect.
弟弟行凶的概率很低
Given the situation at the victim's home,
根据死者家中的情况
it seems likely to be a revenge killing.
极有可能是仇杀
[The victim had quite a temper.]
哥哥脾气不太好
[He often got into arguments with neighbors]
经常因为占地问题
[over land disputes.]
和邻家发生争吵
[He's even been in fights before, causing]
还曾因为打架
[trouble at the village chief's place.]
闹到了里正那里
[In his business dealings,]
做生意呢
[he often clashed with others,]
也常常跟人不和
[making quite a few enemies.]
得罪了不少人
It's possible that the murderer
不排除
seized this opportunity to kill him,
凶手借此机会杀人
and then frame the victim's brother.
然后嫁祸于死者的弟弟
If this is indeed a revenge killing,
若是仇杀
the murderer must have harbored
那凶手跟死者
deep-seated hatred for the victim.
应该有深仇大恨
Killing alone would be one thing,
光杀人也就罢了
but why took
还要把死者的头颅
the victim's head?
也带走
What's the motive behind that?
这是为什么
Setting aside the motive for now,
抛开作案动机不说
can you two figure out
二位可能推断出
what weapon was used?
是什么凶器所致
Ease your mind, Lord Mo,
莫刺史不要着急
let us examine the corpse thoroughly.
待我们细细检查一下
Let's wrap things up for today.
今日就到这儿吧
I'm famished.
我饿了
Lord Mo, I shall now depart.
莫刺史
Farewell.
告辞
You said we should investigate first.
你不是说先查案吗
Why are you suddenly hungry?
怎么突然就饿了
Besides,
再说了
we're not in Xiang'an right now,
我们现在不是在襄安
how can you...
你怎么就
I can't help it; I'm starving.
反正此刻我就是饿了
Didn't you mention
你不是说
you'd prepare medicinal cuisine for me?
要给我做药膳吗
Where is it?
哪儿呢
Make medicinal cuisine?
做药膳
With these hands, seriously?
你确定要用这双手
What's the matter?
怎么了
These hands just examined a corpse.
这可是刚刚验过尸的手
Are you really OK with eating food
用这双手做出的药膳
prepared with these hands?
你确定你能吃得下
YES 路 I 路AM.
吃得下
JUST 路 YOU 路 WAIT.
你等着
Now this is more like it.
这还差不多
Seeing that he didn't even
看他今日连个接风宴
prepare a welcoming feast,
都不给准备
I was concerned that
我还担心啊
this stingy governor might also
这个小气的莫刺史
skimp on our accommodations.
会在客房上也苛待我们
Jing Lin.
景林
Watch your words!
慎言
Lord Mo's diligence in governance sets
莫刺史勤政爱民
him apart as an exceptional official
是百姓口中
in the eyes of the populace.
不可多得的好官
A feast matters not.
一个接风宴而已
What truly matters is
能真正为百姓做事
being able to serve the citizens.
才是最重要的
I checked;
我去看了
the kitchen here is quite decent.
他们这儿的厨房不错
As soon as my lady returned,
夫人一回来
she went cooking for you.
就去给您炖药膳了
Help me with this!
帮我拿一下
Lad?
小孩
Why are you here?
怎么是你
Where's your mast...
你师
Where's your sis?
你姐姐呢
As soon as she came back,
姐姐一回来
I pestered her to teach me her skills.
我就缠着她教我本领
She gladly agreed.
她爽快答应
In the end, she took me to the kitchen,
结果是把我领到厨房
showed me how to make medicinal cuisine,
教了一遍怎么煮药膳
and then hurried off
她就急匆匆离开
to meet her "soulmate."
去见杵臼好友了
I was left in the kitchen for four hours.
留下我守着锅两个时辰
Soulmate?
杵臼好友
"Youths of Yingzhou tire of the plains,"
营州少年厌原野
"in fox fur coats, they hunt by the walls."
狐裘蒙茸猎城下
[The password is correct,]
暗号对了
[but why is it a male voice?]
可怎么是男声
[Wait,]
不对
[this voice sounds familiar.]
这声音还很熟悉
[Why...]
怎么
[is it you?]
是你
"Youths of Ying tire of the plains,"
营州少年厌原野
"in fox fur coats, they hunt by the walls."
狐裘蒙茸猎城下
"Many cups of nomad wine leaves them sober,"
虏酒千钟不醉人
"at ten, the nomad kids are adept horsemen."
胡儿十岁能骑马
I, Chi,
在下小池池
humbly greet you, Lady Yan.
幸会啊 六娘
Chi?
小池池
you're evidently a gentleman;
你明明是郎君
why did you trick me into thinking
为什么要骗我说是
you were a girl from Jiangnan?
江南小娘子呢
Honestly, I didn't mean to deceive you.
其实也不是我想骗你
It's just that when you
只是你这
replied to my first letter,
第一次回信的时候
you started to refer to me as a fair lady.
就叫我小娘子了
I...
我
Well, why did you use
那谁让你用的是
a floral paper for ladies?
女子的花笺
It was filled with a pleasant aroma
那笺上又香气扑鼻的
and had flower petals mixed in.
还夹带着花瓣
My dear, you
郎君
promised to write lyrics for my new song,
你说帮我新曲作词
but it's been over a month now.
这都一月有余了
When will you get around to it?
什么时候给我写啊
Sure, sure...
写写写
Deliver it to the Ministry of Justice.
帮我将信送去刑部
Thanks.
多谢了
My lord,
吴主事
following our recent public appeal
这是我们前些日子
for leads on difficult cases,
对外公告
these are the replies
征集疑难案件线索后的
we received.
来信
I've organized the letters
我已按照地域
by region.
都整理好了
The one on top is...
最上面的这个是呢
Throw them away.
扔了扔了
Can't you understand what I'm saying?
本官的话听不懂吗
If you're really bored,
要实在闲得没事
go clean the floor.
擦地去
"Thoughts on Difficult Cases?"
刑部疑案之我见
I thought
我只当
it was some damsel form Jiangnan who
是哪家江南的闺秀
also enjoys investigating and analyzing,
和我一样喜欢探案分析
which was why I sent my first reply.
这才有了第一封回信
This "Chi" was
这小池池
actually a name I randomly came up with.
其实是我随手起的名
The flower
这花
was borrowed from someone else.
是别人借给我的
So I actually made a mistake.
那我叫错了
Why didn't you correct me
你为什么后来回信
in your later replies?
不纠正我呀
Actually, I was thinking,
其实我是这么想的
since we exchange letters,
既然我们是笔友
it doesn't matter whether I'm a young lord
那无论我是小郎君也好
or a fair lady. It doesn't affect
或是小娘子也罢
our friendship through letters,
也不影响我们以笔会友
to converse about the world,
谈天说地
and to delve into our cases together,
交流案情
right?
不是吗
That's true.
也对
Now that you mention it,
你这么说来
it feels much more enjoyable.
倒是更畅快
By the way,
对了
I didn't know what you liked, so
我也不知道你喜欢什么
I specially sought out the only copy of
我就特地去寻了一本
"Strange Weaponry from the Western Regions"
《西域奇技录》的孤本
This book
这本书中
documents unique tools and techniques
记录了西域
from the Western Regions.
独有的工具以及技法
Take a look.
你看看
See if you like it.
你喜不喜欢
Thank you!
谢谢
I love it!
我很喜欢
Hold on,
等等
It's this page.
就是这页
Take a close look at this
你仔细观察一下
curved blade on this page.
这页的弯刀
After you left today,
今日你走之后
I went to check the corpse again.
我又观察了一下
The wound on the headless corpse,
这无头尸的伤口
given its angle and smoothness,
从伤口的角度
suggests that it was not
以及平整度来看
caused by a straight blade,
应该不是直刃所致
but rather by a curved one.
而是曲刃
[So based on my judgment,]
所以根据我的判断
[the murder weapon should be a special]
这作案凶器
curved blade that cuts through iron
应该是一把
as easily as it cuts through air.
削铁如泥的特制弯刀
I've seen this type of curved blade
这种弯刀
at the border of Xichen.
我在西辰的边境见过
The one on this page,
这页纸上的弯刀
the edge
只有刃口
shows slight differences from
与死者颈部的刃口
the wound on the victim's neck.
有微小的差别
The structure is nearly identical,
构造近乎相似
so whether this is the one
所以究竟是不是这把
still requires further investigation.
还有待我们继续勘察
A curved blade from the Western Regions?
西域弯刀
No wonder I've been racking my brains
怪不得我今日苦思冥想
all day and still couldn't figure out
也没能想到
what the murder weapon was.
用的是什么凶器
It turns out to be a weapon
原来是我
I've never encountered before.
从未见过的凶器
Looks like I really need to
看来我真得
study this book thoroughly
好好读一下这本书了
and learn more about exotic weapons.
多认识一些西域兵器
Maybe I can even
也许还能在这里面
find clues in here.
找到线索
I came to Gannan this time
我这次来甘南道
not only to investigate cases,
除了查案
but also for something more important.
还有件更重要的事
Greetings, Lord Commander.
大阁领
Lord Mo is weary
莫刺史今日疲惫
and has retired
早早就寝
early tonight.
不便相见
It'd be best if you also returned to rest.
您也早些回去歇息吧
Please convey to Lord Mo that
替我转告莫刺史
I will return another day for a chat.
改日我再来畅叙
Yes, my lord.
小的明白
Please have a safe trip back.
大阁领请
Like a dream, a fairy, suddenly fading away;
如梦如仙忽零落
where's the evening glow gone, leaving the screen empty?
暮霞何处绿屏空
So,
所以
long before the incident in Xiang'an City,
早在襄安城出事之前
the human traffickers in Gannan
甘南道的人贩子手里
already had the fire moth jade.
就已经有了火蛾玉
That's right.
没错
The Fire Moth Sect has
火蛾门在甘南道
deeply infiltrated Gannan,
渗透之深远
far beyond our imagination.
远超我们的想象
During my investigation,
我这一路暗查过来
I found that many locals
发现不少当地的民众
secretly worship the Fire Moth Sect.
偷偷信奉着火蛾门
From Xiang'an to Province Ying,
从襄安到营州
I always felt
我总觉得
that behind the Fire Moth Sect,
火蛾门的背后
there is an invisible hand
有一双无形之手
setting up a grand scheme.
在布一个大局
And the figure behind this scheme
而且这布局之人
must be someone with immense power.
定是个势力滔天之人
Unknowingly,
不知不觉
we've been chatting for so long.
都已经聊了这么久了
It's late at night;
夜深了
I should head back.
我该回去了
Then we'll
那我们
talk again next time.
下次再聊
What about my gift?
我的礼物呢
You didn't forget to prepare it, did you?
你不会没准备吧
I did prepare it,
准备倒是准备了
but,
但是吧
it's not quite suitable for you.
不太适合你
You probably won't like it.
你肯定不喜欢
Next time,
下一次
I'll buy you
下次我给你买一个
something else.
更新的
You didn't even show it to me.
你都没给我看一眼
How do you know if I like it or not?
你又怎知我喜不喜欢呢
You insist on seeing it yourself.
是你自己非要看的
Alright,
好了
now you saw it.
你看到了
It doesn't suit you, right?
死心了吧
It's not right to take back a gift
哪有送别人的礼物
after it's been offered.
收回去的道理
Besides,
再说了
I really like it.
我很喜欢
I just happen to need one
我刚好就差一个
hairpin...
发簪
So,
这样
put it on for me.
亲手帮我戴上吧
How does it look?
如何
Does it suit me?
好看吗
[Why did the candle suddenly go out?]
蜡烛怎么突然灭了
[Is it...]
难道
It looks good, quite good.
好看 挺好看的
It's getting late.
时候不早了
I really should head back.
我真的该走了
So long!
告辞啊
It's so late,
这么晚了
Are you planning to keep watch for me?
是打算为我守夜吗
Why are you still dawdling?
还愣着干吗
Come over and sleep.
快过来休息了
[Forget it,]
算了
[it's not like]
又不是
[we haven't slept in the same bed before.]
没在一张床上睡过
[If I catch a cold,]
若得了风寒
[that would be self-inflicted suffering.]
那才是自讨苦吃
Is that Pan Chi
那个潘驰
really your type?
就这么合你胃口吗
What do you mean by that?
什么合我胃口
Like conducting investigations?
你说探案啊
I do have quite a good rapport with him.
我跟他确实挺有默契的
Hey!
你
What are you doing?
你这是做甚
If you keep this up,
你再这样
I will go all out!
我就不客气了
Going all out?
不客气
I'm curious to see
我倒是要看看
what that is like?
你要怎么个不客气法
Shen Du,
沈渡
why are you awake at this late hour,
你大半夜不睡觉
acting all crazy?
发什么疯呢
Someone's beating the drum to seek justice.
有人击鼓伸冤
Who was beating the drum at the gate,
堂下何人击鼓
and what grievance does he have?
又有何冤情
In response to my lord,
回大人的话
my name is Du Fusheng,
草民名叫杜福生
a merchant of herbal medicine.
是一名药材商人
Today is
今日
the wedding day of my youngest daughter,
正是家中小女杜小婉
Du Xiaowan and Li Hongfa's son,
与李鸿发之子李子墨
Li Zimo.
成亲之日
Unexpectedly, a strange incident occurred.
却不承想发生了怪事
My daughter
小女
was present when she was welcomed in,
在迎进门的时候还在
but after the wedding banquet, when they
婚宴结束
were about to share the nuptial cup,
入房行合卺之礼的时候
she suddenly went missing.
却发现小女不见了
[The incident happened so abruptly.]
事发突然
[Despite our search, she remained missing.]
又遍寻不见
[So we came to report to the authorities.]
我们这才来报官
On a joyous occasion with many guests,
大喜之日宾客众多
this will be challenging to investigate.
这可不好查
Do you have a guest list?
你们可有宾客名单
Yes, yes,
有有
it's right here.
在这里
Bring it up.
呈上来
Was the marriage between your two families
你们两家的婚事
based on mutual consent?
可是你情我愿
Yes, my lord,
自然是
Xiaowan and I are well-matched,
我与小婉本就门当户对
and we cherish each other.
互相爱慕
[This outcome took everyone by surprise.]
可谁会知发生这样的事
[I implore you, my lord,]
求莫刺史大人
to find Xiaowan for me.
定要找到小婉
Dispatch teams
来人
to both families for investigation.
带人去两家查看
Focus particularly on the Li family;
尤其是李家
they require a meticulous examination.
要仔细勘察
Look for any
看看有没有什么
evidence that may have been overlooked.
留下的痕迹
Pay special attention to
着重看一看
the entries and exits of all doors.
各处门禁的出入
Understood!
是
Lord Mo,
莫刺史
the guest list's been thoroughly checked,
宾客名单已经核对过了
most guests are still present,
大部分人仍在
with only a few unaccounted for.
只有少数人不在
Locate them!
找
Bring everyone back once found.
找到之后全都带回来
Yes!
是
What is it?
怎么了
My lord,
大人
if we all go out to search,
若是我们都出去找人了
there may not be enough personnel
这现场查案恐怕
to investigate the scene.
人手不够
Lord Mo,
莫刺史
if you lack manpower,
若人手不足
my guardsmen can assist.
我的内卫可以帮忙
Then I'll count on you, Lord Shen.
那就有劳沈大阁领了
Jing Lin.
景林
My lord.
是
Proceed.
去吧
You all follow me.
你们跟我走
You all come with me as well.
你们也跟我走
[Li Hongfa's family is affluent.]
李鸿发家境富裕
[The wedding house must be]
新房必是
[meticulously decorated.]
精心布置过才是
[There are no signs of]
屋内并没有
[a struggle inside.]
打斗过的痕迹
It appears that something occurred in here.
看来新房中发生过什么
In a fit of rage,
气愤之余
someone damaged this.
有人抓坏了这里
This is supposed to be a celebration,
明明是办喜事
yet everything here feels off.
这里却处处透露着古怪
Furthermore,
更何况
just looking at this door frame,
这个门框一看
it's clearly been refurbished,
都是翻新过
yet there are signs of peeling paint.
但居然有掉漆的痕迹
This definitely indicates a problem.
这一定有问题
I share your thoughts on this.
我也是这样想的
By the way,
对了
have you made any discoveries?
你那边有什么发现吗
I passed through the living room,
我途经客厅
and also went by the corner arbor
还路过了抄廊角亭
and the rockery,
和假山
but along the way,
可这一路上
I found nothing of note.
却没有任何发现
That makes sense.
那就对了
The bride didn't leave of her own accord;
新娘不是自愿离开
she was abducted by someone she knew,
而是被熟识之人劫持
taken out through the back window.
从后窗带走的
With such a pressing case at hand,
眼下有这么要紧的案子
are you two still in the mood
二位还有心情
to chat idly here?
在这里闲聊
I'm analyzing the case with Lady Yan.
我和颜令史在分析案情
How is that mere idle chatter?
何为闲聊
Besides,
再说了
we've already reached a conclusion.
我们已经有了结论
The bride
新娘
was indeed taken through this back window.
就是从这后窗被劫的
Alright.
行了
Time for certain individuals to get to work.
现在该轮到某些人忙活
Hurry and issue orders to search for her.
赶紧吩咐下去去寻人吧
Very well,
那好
Mr. Pan, please lead the way.
请潘郎君领路
Along with my guardsmen
和我的内卫一同
to pursue the suspects.
追缉嫌犯
Why did you leave in the middle?
你们为何半途离席
A servant of mine reported
家中下人来报
that my child fell sick,
孩子病了
and my husband
我那口子
is unable to care for the child.
也不会看孩子呀
It was already quite late.
这当时天色都这么晚了
I couldn't
难不成
keep this up until dawn, right?
还要折腾到天明去啊
My lord,
刺史大人
please,
这件事情
don't mention this
您可千万
to my wife.
别跟我夫人说啊
I came here with the purpose
我也是过来
of checking on my mistress as well.
看看我那外室
At the wedding,
那当时婚礼上
did anything
有没有发生什么
unusual occur?
奇怪的事情
Nothing at all.
没有呀
Except for that...
除了那个
Xu Jize performed quite well.
许己则做得出色点以外
I didn't notice anything else
我倒没看出有什么
out of the ordinary.
其他不同的
As for Xu Jize,
这许己则
he certainly had a tough time.
也真是难为他了
Being a wedding attendant
傧相这一行
is not an easy task.
本就不太好干
There are very few in Yingzhou.
营州从事的奇少
But I heard that
不过我听说
he has no recommendation.
他也是无人引荐
He had no way to secure a public position,
招考无门
so he became an wedding attendant.
这才去做的傧相
Let's go, everyone.
请吧 各位
Where's Xu Jize?
那个许已则呢
Why isn't he here?
他怎么不在
My lord,
回大人
he hasn't been located.
没找到
In that case,
如此看来
[Xu Jize]
许己则
[is the only one who left early]
是唯一一个提前离席
[and had the opportunity]
且能近距离
[to get close to the bride.]
接触新娘的人
Lady Yan,
颜令史
do you think
你觉得
the culprit could be Xu Jize?
凶犯会不会是许己则呢
At this moment, I can't provide an answer
现时我也无法回答
to that question.
你这个问题
Before the case is resolved,
案子未破之前
everyone present
在场的每一个人
is a suspect.
都有嫌疑
His absence from the scene
而他此刻不在现场
only suggests that
只能代表
his suspicion is even more pronounced.
他的嫌疑更深一重
At the end of the day,
最终
we still need evidence and witnesses.
还是要物证人证才行
You are Lord Commander's wife indeed.
果然是沈大阁领的夫人
Though at a young age,
年纪虽轻
you speak and act with great precision,
说话办事滴水不漏
and have your own set of principles.
自有一套规矩在
From what you just said,
听莫刺史一言
it's clear you know
是对我们家大阁领
my husband well.
很了解
Detain them in the governor's office.
把他们都押回刺史府
My lord!
是
Let's go.
走吧
Please, don't kill me!
求你们不要杀我
Don't kill me!
别杀我 别杀我
Who are you?
你是何人
Why are you fleeing at this hour?
为何夜半在此惊慌逃窜
My name is Xu Jize.
我叫许己则
Please, don't kill me!
别杀我 别 别杀我
Over there...
那边
Someone died over there!
那边死人了 那边
Xu Jize?
许己则
Are you that wedding attendant?
你是那个傧相
Hand him over to Lord Mo.
把人交给莫刺史
You are quite something, huh?
好你个沈渡啊
Pushed a civilian out to intercept a suspect?
把一介平民丢出去拦路
Is this the style of the Imperial Guard?
这就是内卫府的作风吗
The style of the Imperial Guard?
内卫府的作风
Is it a machine that kills many,
是杀人如麻的机器
or a demon that stops children
还是夜止小儿啼哭的
from crying at night?
瘟神
Which one does
潘郎君想要的是
Mr. Pan prefer?
哪一种啊
Lord Commander, you are quite self-aware.
沈大阁领贵有自知之明
I admire that.
潘某佩服
Really.
佩服
But since we're at this point,
不过话都说到这儿了
let's speak frankly.
不如就把话说开吧
You constantly target me,
你这处处针对我
always pick on me.
处处看我不顺眼
If so,
既然如此
why did you insist on dragging me
你干吗非得拉着我
to pursue the culprit together?
一起追凶呢
Mr. Pan, you are also self-aware.
潘郎君也有自知之明
You know you're in my way.
自知碍了我的眼
Why do you keep showing up?
为何还频频出现
I'm doing this out of necessity
我那是破案需求
for the sake of solving the case.
迫不得已
Necessity?
破案需求
Showing off even if I was at the scene.
见我到场便得寸进尺
Was that also out of necessity?
也是迫不得已
[Help!]
救命啊
Why did it suddenly become quiet?
怎么没声了
You,
你
go down there and take a look.
下去看看
Why should I go down?
凭什么让我下去
You, an honorable commander
你一个堂堂大阁领
are still here.
在这里
Who knows what was happening down there?
底下什么情况谁知道
Besides,
再说了
if I go down
我要下去
and get killed, what then?
被别人杀害了怎么办
If you die,
你若是死了
I will collect your body,
我会替你收尸
build a grave for you,
为你建坟立冢
and ensure your spirit
不会让你的魂魄
doesn't wander about,
飘荡在外
so as not to scare others.
以免吓到别人
Why are you so sharp-tongued?
你这个人嘴怎么这么毒
You're at a loss for words, aren't you?
说不过我是吧
Get your arse down there!
下去
I'll assess the situation first.
我先看看什么情况
You are?
你是
Don't be afraid. I'm here to rescue you!
别怕 我来救你上去
Lord Shen!
大阁领
You are that bride from today's wedding?
你就是今天那位新娘
Yes,
是
I am Du Xiaowan.
我就是杜小婉
Save me, my lord!
大人救我呀 大人
There's another person down there,
下面还有一个人
another one!
还有一个
At least you have a conscience.
还算你有良心
I climbed up on my own.
我自己爬上来了
My back!
我的腰
You call yourself a commander,
亏你还是个大阁领
yet you have no honor.
你到底懂不懂江湖道义
You keep stabbing me in the back!
一次又一次陷害我
I wasn't talking about you.
不是你
There's another one.
还有一个
A dead man!
一个死人
You all,
你们几个
go secure the perimeter.
去周围查探一下
Jing Lin,
景林
check if there's anything
去看看下面
unusual down there.
还有没有异常
Understood!
是
Lord Shen,
报告大阁领
there's nothing unusual down there.
下面没有异常
[Lord Shen,]
大阁领
[the perimeter has been secured.]
周围都检查过了
[Nothing is unusual.]
并无异常
On our way here,
这一路上
we all saw
我们都看见了
the nervous-looking suspect
那个神情紧张的
who is the wedding attendant.
傧相嫌犯
Why do you keep investigating elsewhere?
你为何还要反复勘察
Are you so sure
你就这么笃定
that he is not the murderer?
这个人不是凶手
I can't be certain
我不能确定
if that man is the murderer or not,
那个人是不是凶手
but my intuition tells me
但我的直觉告诉我
that this incident
这件事情
is not as simple as
没有我们看到的
it appears.
那么简单
I've truly broadened my horizons,
在下算是开了眼界了
witnessing how the esteemed commander
这堂堂大阁领破案
solves cases with
靠的就是个
his extraordinary intuition.
天赋异禀的直觉
Lord Shen,
大阁领
do you want to continue investigating?
还要继续查吗
Let's head back.
撤吧
-Where is she? -You bastard!
你说 人呢 你个畜生
Give me back my daughter!
还我女儿
Where have you hidden her?
你把人藏哪儿去了
Where is Xiaowan?
小婉呢
Tell me!
你说呀
Animal!
畜生
Hold your tongue
公堂之上
and behave in court!
不得放肆
Xu Jize,
许己则
Let me ask you,
本官问你
regarding Lady Du's disappearance,
杜娘子失踪一案
is it related to you?
可与你有关
I'm being wronged, my lord!
冤枉啊 刺史大人
Her abduction
杜娘子被人掳走一事
has nothing to do with me.
跟我没有关系
I was trying to rescue her!
我只是想去营救
Do you have any witnesses or evidence
那你可有人证物证
to support this claim?
证明这一点
My lord,
大人
the event unfolded abruptly,
当时事发突然
and in my haste to rescue her,
我也是着急去救人
there were no witnesses.
并没有人看到这一切
However, every word I speak is the truth.
但我所言句句属实
I implore you to see the clarity.
还请大人明鉴
So, there're no witnesses or evidence?
那就是没有人证物证了
My lady,
夫人
Lord Shen has returned.
大阁领回来了
You're finally back!
你们可算回来了
Did you find anything?
可有什么发现
The bride has been located,
新娘找到了
and a corpse was brought back.
还带回来一具尸体
A fatality?
死人了
How are you doing?
那你怎么样
Are you injured?
有没有受伤
I am not someone
我岂是别人
who can be easily harmed.
可以随随便便伤到的人
My lady, ease your mind.
夫人不必忧心
Then what happened to you?
你又怎么了
There are bruises all over your hands,
怎么手上都是伤
and you're covered in mud!
身上还有泥啊
You should ask your
这就该问你那
smart arse husband about this.
聪明的夫君了
Along the way,
这一路上
I did all the dirty and hard work,
脏活累活我一个人干
and in the end, he took all the credit.
最后功劳一个人全落了
Anyway,
无论如何
the fact that you both returned safely
你们能够平安归来
is good enough.
就是好事
By the way,
对了
how did you bring back
那个新娘子
the bride?
你们是怎么带回来的
Tell me the details.
快把细节跟我讲讲
First, we encountered
先是在半路上
a suspect
遇到了
who was fleeing in panic.
惊慌逃窜的嫌疑人
Then we discovered
然后发现了
the bride trapped in a well.
被困在窖井中的新娘
In that well,
这窖井之中
besides the bride,
除了新娘之外
there was also a corpse,
还有一具尸体
so we brought them both back.
所以就一并带回来了
The suspect you mentioned
你所说的那个嫌疑人
is the Xu Jize who was brought back by
便是之前内卫带回来的
the guardsmen, right?
那个许己则吗
Exactly, the attendant from the wedding.
正是婚礼那个傧相
After you left,
你们离开之后
I also investigated the guests
我也对赴宴的宾客
at the wedding.
进行了调查
According to them, Xu Jize
他们口中的许己则
is quite a good person.
那可是大好人一个
On the surface,
明面上
he doesn't seem to have a motive.
他也并没有作案的动机
Whether he is the murderer or not
他是不是凶手
still needs to be investigated.
还有待查明
By the way,
对了
when I was at the bottom of the well,
在井底下的时候
I remember seeing a sack.
我还记得有一个麻袋
That sack
那个麻袋
was likely used
应该是用来
to abduct the bride.
掳走新娘用的吧
Why didn't you mention
这么重要的证据
such crucial evidence earlier?
刚才为什么不说
I'm not your subordinate.
我又不是你的下属
Why should I
干吗什么事
report everything to you?
都向你报备啊
Enough,
好了
you both should go get changed.
你们快去换身衣服吧
I'll wait for you in the court.
我在大堂等你们
This is a case for the Yingzhou magistrate,
这是营州府衙的事
and should be dealt by Lord Mo himself.
理应由莫刺史自行决断
I won't be joining you.
我便不去堂前了
[My lord, with no solid evidence]
大人无凭无据
[you can't arrest me.]
就将我抓来
[I'm being wronged!]
草民冤枉啊
[I risked my life...]
我是为了救杜娘子
What's the status of the interrogation?
审到哪环了
[...trying to save Lady Du!]
才以身犯险的
I missed some details earlier,
刚才错过了一些
and now I'm completely at a loss.
我现在也毫无头绪
And she wasn't harmed,
而她也未受到伤害
just sprained her ankle.
只是崴到了脚
My lord,
刺史大人
shouldn't you
是不是该对我
change your attitude towards me?
换一种态度
This guy really knows how
此人还真是
to flatter himself.
会给自己戴高帽
Before any evidence is presented,
证据没上之前
he distances himself from everything.
把自己撇得一干二净
And he requests to be treated nicely.
还要当堂求礼待
I've truly never encountered
我还真是第一次看到
such an arrogant individual.
如此嚣张的人
If a tree has no bark,
树若无皮
it will surely perish.
必死无疑
A person without shame
人不要脸
is unimaginable!
天下无敌
You won't admit it until
你这是
you're presented with the evidence, right?
不见棺材不落泪啊
Lord Mo,
莫刺史
I have new evidence to present.
潘某有新的证物要呈
Xu Jize,
许己则
do you recognize this?
这个东西
Does this look familiar to you?
你看着眼不眼熟
This item has nothing to do with me.
此物与我无关
it must belong to the murderer.
定是凶手的东西
It's that dead person
都是那个死者
who abducted Lady Du.
害的杜娘子
I was just trying to save her!
我就是来救人的
Don't wrong the innocent!
你们不要冤枉无辜啊
Then tell me in detail
那你把你所看到的
what you saw.
细细说来
I...
我
I just went to the restroom,
我当时就是上了个茅房
and when I came out,
出来的时候
I saw the culprit
就看到贼人
abducting Lady Du.
将杜娘子掳走了
[The incident happened so suddenly.]
当时事发突然
[I didn't have time]
我也没来得及
[to notify anyone else.]
通知其他人
[Worried about her life,]
又挂念杜娘子的安危
I went alone to rescue her.
就独自前往营救了
How can you expect anyone to believe
你这无凭无据
such baseless claims?
怎能让人相信
For God's sake,
天知地知
everything I said is true.
我所说的句句属实
I urge you all to see clearly!
还请各位大人明察
Let me clarify for you.
我来帮你说吧
You and the deceased are accomplices.
你和死者就是同伙
Together, you abducted Lady Du,
你们一起将杜娘子掳走
and then, due to a falling out,
然后因为不和
you killed your accomplice.
你将同伙杀害
To cover up your tracks,
为了掩盖事实
you pretended to be a good person,
将自己装成一个好人
washing your hands
把所有的责任
of all responsibility.
跟自己撇得一干二净
My lord,
刺史大人
I'm being wronged!
冤枉啊
I truly didn't kill anyone!
我真的没有杀人
I don't even know the deceased;
我跟死者根本不认识
why would I kill him?
我为什么会杀了他呢
[When a person is lying,]
人在说慌的时候
[they tend to blink excessively, often]
会不断眨眼
[accompanied by a nose-wrinkling gesture.]
还伴有拱鼻子的动作
[But just now, when he claimed]
而刚才他说
[he didn't kill anyone,]
他没有杀人的时候
[his demeanor was remarkably resolute,]
神情却异常坚定
[indicating he wasn't lying.]
可见他不是说谎
Since you don't know the deceased,
你和死者既然不认识
how did you witness him being murdered?
你是怎么看到他被害的
I didn't see the murder
我也没有亲眼看到
take place;
死者被杀
when I arrived,
我过去的时候
the person was already dead.
人已经死了
According to you,
按你说
you saw someone
你看到有人
abducting Lady Du.
将杜娘子掳走
What characteristics does he have?
这个人可有什么特征
At that moment,
当时
the lighting wasn't very good,
光线不是很亮
so I couldn't see clearly.
我也没看清楚
However,
不过
based on the deceased's height
以死者的身高
and demeanor,
和神态来看
he must have been
应该就是
the one who abducted Lady Du.
掳走杜娘子的那个人
You're only judging
只是从身高
by height and demeanor?
和神态来判断
Didn't you notice
难道就没有注意到
any other distinguishing features?
其他什么特征吗
The event unfolded so suddenly, so
事发突然
I didn't pay attention to anything else.
我也没多留意其他的
My lord, Du Xiaowan has arrived!
大人 杜小婉到
Xiaowan, my dear Xiaowan!
婉儿 我的婉儿
It's alright now, my girl.
没事了啊 孩子
Everything is fine.
好了
Du Xiaowan,
杜小婉
[you are the key witness.]
你是当事人
[Please recount everything]
将今日发生之事
[that happened today.]
一一道来
Xiaowan,
小婉
we have already made our vows.
我们已经拜过天地
You are now my wife.
你就是我李子墨的妻子
I, Li Zimo, swear to God here
我李子墨在此对天发誓
that I will never hold a grudge
绝对不会因为今日之事
because of today's events.
心存芥蒂
Lady Du, I understand
杜娘子
that women value their reputation,
我知道女子都注重声誉
which makes it difficult for you to speak,
让你无法开口
but have you considered that
但你可有想过
if the murderer isn't brought to justice,
如果不将凶手绳之以法
more young women
以后还会有更多小娘子
will fall victim in the future?
难逃魔掌
They may not all be as fortunate as you
她们也未必都如你一样
to have a chance of being rescued.
有获救的机会
My lady,
夫人
let's help Lord Mo
我们合力帮助刺史
capture the murderer,
捉到凶手
alright?
可好
After we performed the wedding rites,
行过天地礼之后
I saw the attendant in the bridal chamber,
我在新房见到了傧相
but then,
但后来
I suddenly fainted
却不知怎么的
[for reasons I don't understand.]
突然晕了过去
[When I came to,]
醒过来时
[I found myself in a sack,]
就已经在麻袋里了
[and I didn't see who had taken me.]
并未看到是谁将我掳走
[I was terrified at that moment,]
我当时害怕极了
[unable to scream,]
又喊不出声来
[only aware that I]
只知道自己
[was trapped in the sack,]
被套在麻袋里
[being carried on someone's shoulder.]
被人扛在肩上奔跑
[After what felt like an eternity,]
过了很久很久
[I was finally set down.]
我才被人放下
Then another person arrived.
后来又来了一个人
Did you hear
那你可有听到
what they were discussing?
他们都说了些什么
I initially thought that person
我原以为那个人
was there to rescue me,
是来救我的
but to my surprise,
却没想到
the two of them were actually accomplices.
他们两个人竟是同伙
They were discussing how
他们在一起商量着
to share me,
要如何分享我
and their words were truly unbearable.
那言语实在是难以入耳
I simply couldn't bring myself to say it.
我实在是说不出口
My lord,
各位大人
my wife has suffered such humiliation.
我夫人受了这样的侮辱
I implore you,
还请各位大人
please punish the murderer severely.
一定要严惩凶手
Mr. Li, rest assured,
李郎君放心
we will ensure the murderer
我们定不会让凶手
does not escape justice.
逍遥法外
Then, I'm not sure what happened,
后来也不知怎么了
but the two of them began to argue.
他们二人争吵了起来
[I made a mistake;]
我搞错了
[let her go.]
把她放了吧
[Be serious!]
你开什么玩笑
[The die is cast;]
木已成舟
[you have to go through with it!]
你不干也得干
[I'll check over there.]
我去那边看看
[After a while, I thought]
过了一会儿
[I heard someone chasing from behind,]
像是听到后面有人追来
[so they discarded me into]
他们便把我丢弃在
[the abandoned well.]
废墟的窖井里
[Before they could cover the well,]
还没等盖好窖井的盖子
[I heard a scream,]
我便听到一声尖叫
[followed by a thud,]
随后就是扑通一声
[as if someone]
好像是有人
[had fallen beside me.]
掉在了我的身边
[The sack loosened,]
麻袋松了
[and I managed to crawl out.]
我便爬了出来
Help!
救命啊
[I heard someone approaching,]
我听到有人前来
[but I was afraid it was]
但我害怕是
[the accomplice who had fled earlier,]
之前逃跑的同伙
so I stopped calling out.
我便不再呼喊
It wasn't until someone
一直到有人
jumped down the well
从井口跳下来
that I was finally rescued.
将我救出
Since you overheard their conversation,
你既然听过二人说话
can you identify by his voice
可否通过声音判断
if that person
那个人
was Xu Jize?
是不是许己则
The situation was dire,
情况危急
and I was terrified.
我害怕极了
I was so scared that my head was spinning,
我怕得脑子嗡嗡响
and I couldn't discern whose voice it was.
听不出是谁的声音了
Lady Du has made it
杜娘子已经说得
quite clear.
很明白了
In her final moments before fainting,
她在晕倒最后的时刻
she saw Xu Jize.
看到的就是许己则
Regardless of if you are the murderer,
不管你是不是杀人凶手
this case
这个案子
is undoubtedly connected to you.
也定与你脱不了干系
I...
我
Xu Jize, you scoundrel!
许己则你个王八蛋
Bastard!
王八蛋
Animal!
畜生
Silence!
肃静
What an animal!
畜生啊
You must not act unruly in court!
公堂之上不得放肆
My lady,
夫人
Lord Shen cannot come in person,
大阁领不便前来
so I was sent to present the evidence
派我将此案证物
to the court.
呈送堂前
There is evidence,
有证物
and there are follow-up actions.
还有后手
Why didn't you report it sooner?
怎不早点禀告
I'm not your subordinate.
我又不是你的下属
Why should I report everything to you?
何须事事与你禀告
No wonder you work under that man;
不愧是他的下属
you're truly petty!
真小心眼
Xu Jize,
许己则
now that it has come to this,
事到如今
what else do you have to say?
你还有何话可说
My lord,
大人
I'm truly wronged!
我真的冤枉
On the wedding day,
新婚之日
it's common for the bride to go
新娘往往整日未食
without food all day
昏睡过去
and fall into a deep sleep.
是经常发生的事
Seeing the bride lacking energy,
一看到新娘精神不振
I immediately left the room
我为了避嫌
to avoid any embarrassment.
立马就退出了房门
Then the culprit abducted the bride,
而后贼人将新娘掳走
and only then did I chase after him!
我才追了出去
Stop trying to weasel out of it!
还在狡辩
What happened after you chased out?
那你追出去之后呢
What did you see? Speak!
看到了什么 说
I'm not sure how far I chased,
我也不知道我追了多远
but then
然后
I saw
然后我就看到
a shadow with a knife.
一个提刀的黑影
The person who abducted Lady Du
掳走杜娘子的人
was lying nearby.
就倒在了旁边
As a mere scholar,
我一介书生
physical strength isn't my forte,
手无缚鸡之力
so I dared not confront him.
万万不敢上前对抗
I turned and ran
我便调头就跑
until I encountered the guardsmen,
直到我遇到了各位大人
which saved my life.
才保住了一条小命
My lady,
大人
what is this for?
这是做什么
Men and women should keep a respectful distance.
男女授受不亲
Mr. Xu, the embroidery on your clothes
许郎君这身衣服的绣样
is truly exquisite.
还真是精妙呢
The peach blossom pattern at the collar,
这领口处的桃花样
I wonder which fair lady
不知道是哪家小娘子
embroidered it for you?
给你绣上的呢